<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The description of Swedland, Gotland, and Finland the auncient estate of theyr kynges, the moste horrible and incredible tiranny of the second Christiern, kyng of Denmarke, agaynst the Swecians, the poleticke attaynyng to the crowne of Gostaue, wyth hys prudent prouidyng for the same. Collected and gathered out of sundry laten aucthors, but chieflye out of Sebastian Mounster. By George North. Set forth accordyng to the order in the Quenes Maiesties iniunction.</title>
            <title>Cosmographia. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Münster, Sebastian, 1489-1552.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848523</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 326:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The description of Swedland, Gotland, and Finland the auncient estate of theyr kynges, the moste horrible and incredible tiranny of the second Christiern, kyng of Denmarke, agaynst the Swecians, the poleticke attaynyng to the crowne of Gostaue, wyth hys prudent prouidyng for the same. Collected and gathered out of sundry laten aucthors, but chieflye out of Sebastian Mounster. By George North. Set forth accordyng to the order in the Quenes Maiesties iniunction.</title>
                  <title>Cosmographia. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Münster, Sebastian, 1489-1552.</author>
                  <author>North, George, gentleman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Awdely, dwelling in litle Britaine Streete, by great S. Bartelmewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1561. The. 28. of October.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Almost entirely a translation from Münster's "Cosmographia" (STC).</note>
                  <note>With a dedication to Thomas Steuckley. Variant: with cancel dedication to Nils Gyllenstierna.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the countrye and kynges of Swecia.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scandinavia --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scandinavia --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:1"/>
            <p>¶ The Deſcription of Swedland, Gotland, and Finland, the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient eſtate of theyr Kynges, the moſte horrible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible tiranny of the ſecond Chriſtiern, kyng of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, agaynſt the Swecians, the poleticke attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to the Crowne of Goſtaue, wyth hys prudent prouidyng for the ſame. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and gathered out of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry laten Aucthors, but chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye out of Sebaſtian Mounſter. By George North.</p>
            <p>¶ Set forth accordyng to the order in the Quenes Maieſties Iniunction.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Iohn Awdely, dwelling in litle Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Streete, by great S. Bartelmewes. Anno <hi>.1561.</hi> The <hi>.28.</hi> of October.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the ryght woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfull, and hys ſynguler good Mayſter, Mayſter Thomas Steuckley Eſquire, hys obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſeruaunt George North wyſheth proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous health, wyth encreaſe of muche worſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient Hiſtoriographers (my ſinguler good Mayſter) for theyr difficult trauayl, merite moſt hye laud, whoſe famous woorkes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueleth to our memory the ſecrete doinges of tyme paſt: and alſo bewrayeth to tyme pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the vnknowen actes of oure Elders. For although by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of Nature, their bodies are kylled: yet lyueth theyr good or euyll deedes, in the euerlaſtyng report of let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters. Amonge theſe none deſerueth more praiſe, nor worthy of more veneracion, then the moſt noble writer Sebaſtian Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter: whoſe large labour greatlye ſurmounteth the doynges of any other. Thys Mounſter both compendiouſly &amp; briefely (and yet elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and truly) entreateth, not onely of one, &amp; hys own natural ſoyle: but generally
<pb facs="tcp:13623:3"/>of al Nacions, the ſituacion of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the maners of theyr people, wyth the ryghtes and vſages of their Princes. In whoſe volume it was my fortune to reade the deſcription of Swedlande, Gothland, &amp; Finland. And findyng theſe Countries to be ſo large and fruitefull, theyr Kynges ſo noble and auncient, &amp; theyr people ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and valiaunt. Conſideryng the vertue of Princes to be a myrrour to looke on, &amp; their vices a terrour to thynke on, &amp; alſo for that ſwyft Fame hath publiſhed the reporte of theſe people vnto vs: I thoughte meete to reduce the ſame hyſtorye into our vulgare tounge, thoughe not ſo copiouſlye and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlye as any learned myght haue done. The ſituacion and naturall lying of theyr great and large Countries, the rytches, fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tillitye and fruitfulnes of the ſame, wyth theyr noble &amp; notable Cities, I haue brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerpaſſed. The old eſtate and auncient raygne of theyr Kinges, with theyr diuers and ſundrye alteracions, ſometyme by the Danes, ſometyme by the Norwayes, and ſometyme by deuiſion among them ſelues.
<pb facs="tcp:13623:3"/>I haue in few words collected. But the hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible and cruel tyranny of the ſecond Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiern kyng of Denmarke, againſt the Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians, and hys iuſt reward for the ſame, the poleticke attaining of King Goſtaue to the crowne, hys triumphant Coronacion, hys prudent gouernyng, with the vertuous pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uidyng for the education &amp; learned inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſte noble Eric nowe Kyng of Swecia, I haue moſt amply declared. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the report hereof out of ſundry Aut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thors, as Iohn Magnus, Archbiſhoppe of Vpſalen, Saxus Grammaticus, and Seba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian Mounſter, whoſe authoritye I haue chieflye folowed. Proferynge the ſame (to your worſhyp) as the fruites of my trauail in your abſence: acknowledging herewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al the remembraunce of my ſeruiceable deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and good wil to your Maſterſhip, whoſe large &amp; ample benefites I haue not ſeldome tymes receyued, with your fauorable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not onely to me, but alſo to euerye one, whoſe nede you knew to want your reliefe. More, what friend remaynes vnrecompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>? any friendſhyp towardes you? What
<pb facs="tcp:13623:4"/>ſtayed hand hath wythdrawen any gyft of yours from him who deſyred it, and whom you thought worthy to receiue it? Beſydes theſe your liberalities, your own trauel in foreyne &amp; ſtraungenacions wyth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnderſtandyng, &amp; almoſt natural ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of theyr languages: importeth you to be as trym a Courtier, as you are knowen to be a worthy Soldiour. I woulde dilate your ſeueral vertues, but I feare to incurre your diſpleaſure thereby, whoſe eares enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearing of your own praiſe, &amp; whoſe tounge thundreth oute the good fame of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Alſo ſome ſclaunderous Sicopha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts would ſaye my pen dyd flowe rather wyth affection and flattery, then wyth troth and veritye. But to ſuche (as neuer learned to ſpeake wel) I anſwer (that beſides the part of a Seruaunt) I haue wayed more your inward natural inclinacion, then your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde franke doynges, althoughe they are ſufficient wytneſſes wyth me of thys my reporte. Moſt humblye deſiryng you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in good part thys my vnlearned labor, that I haue vnder the defence of your good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:13623:4"/>putin publycke prynt, whyche if it bee thankfully taken, may encourage me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to attempt larger workes, whereby I truſte as well to profyt my Countrye, as to content my ſelfe. Wyſhinge the proſperous ſucceſſe of Fortune to cal you to your harts deſyre, wyth the fruitfull continuaunce of helth betwene you and my Myſtres, whoſe goodnes both I and myne haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes aboundauntly taſted, to whom I wyſh lyke proſperitye. Whoſe mynde is frayted wyth a nomber of ſober vertues.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your bounde Seruaunt, as I haue euer ſemed George North.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:5"/>
            <head>¶ The deſcription of the moſt floriſhyng Countrye of Gothia, or Gotlande, wyth the auncient raygne of theyr noble Princes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hys woord Gotlande in the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine toung doth interpretat a good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of good land. And amongſt the Northeaſt Regions, thys Countrye of the Gothes is moſt fertylit. It is alſo to be prere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reſt, for the aboundaunt yeldyng or all maner of fruites and honye, and chiefelye for that it hathe ſuche goodly paſtures, whereby their cattel are fed both great and fat,<note place="margin">The fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of Goth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> full of large Foreſtes, with apt &amp; pleſaunt Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. They haue great ſtore of all maner of Merchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp; in euery place is found ſuch plenty of vſual neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, that their ſuperfluities ſuffiſeth to enterchaunge wyth others, aboundyng with precious turres and met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, but chiefely wyth Copper.</p>
            <p>The Gothes &amp; the Swecians tyme out of mynde, &amp; euen from the beginning or their beynge: haue vnſted &amp; knyt themſelues in leage &amp; amitye,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns haue tyme out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nve, bene vnder one Kyng.</note> both vnder one law and one King. And alſo they haue apointed the confines &amp; boundes of both Countries to be as one kyngdome. Yet haue they often tymes occaſion being offered (&amp; as thoſe chaunces are wount) ſequeſtred &amp; deuided them ſelues the one from the other, and eche nacion haue had their ſeueral king. Notwithſtanding their deuiſion was neuer certayne, neyther dyd it longe remayne betwene them: but that they were ioyned agayne with contented ſubiection vnder the aucthority and gouernment of one
<pb facs="tcp:13623:5"/>Prince. At home &amp; neare hand agaynſt their neighbours the Swecians haue euer preuayled:<note place="margin">Nereh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and againſt theyr neigh bours, the Swecians haue euer ſtooriſhed, but abroade the Goth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but abroade in far &amp; ſtraunge Countries, the glorye of the Gothes wyth their mighty and bloudy bartels by the report of Fame haue greatly exceded. They wreſtled of long tyme with the Romaynes, &amp; being ouercommed, they woulde for a while be quiet: but attempting againe the doubtfull ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard of battel, they haue with great diſcomfiture and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Romaines, ſuppreſſed &amp; ouerthrowen their mighty and almoſt inuincible armies. Alſo not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome times with equal victorye,<note place="margin">The gothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſackt Rome they poſſen Italy, they occupyed Fraunce, &amp; made ſure four da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in Spayne.</note> or litle loſſe they haue departed. And at length treading downe &amp; ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming their whole Empire: they paſt through Italy, where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great waſt &amp; deſtruction they ſacked Rome. They poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed Italy no ſmal tyme, they occupyed Fraunce, and they grounded them ſelues ſo in Spayne, that theyr chiefe Nobilitie dothe diſcende from them, as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne hiſtories doth mencion.</p>
            <p>Gothland boundeth wyth his Northe limites to the South of Swecia, &amp; lyeth from the Weſt to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of Norway,<note place="margin">The noble cities of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omrs.</note> which are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lymites of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, to the mouth of the Riuer Trolheta, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the South and the Eaſt it ioyneth on the ſea. The townes &amp; cities of this Country, be many and great, Lodhuſia a Porte towne, wher great trafike is vſed, Wald burgurbs hath a ſtrong &amp; fayre Caſtel, Halmſtat, Elſinburg, Landſkro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Calmaria with a goodly Caſtell. Stegholm, Suderco pia, Norcopia, Lidercopia a city that ſtandes vpon the riuer of Vener, Vaſten &amp; Huetland <hi>.2.</hi> trymme townes. Veſtrogothia a Dukedom, whoſe cities be Scaris and Varnem, where are the Sepulchres &amp; graues of theyr auncient kyngs. Oſtrogothia a Dukedom, whoſe cities
<pb facs="tcp:13623:6"/>be Schemingt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; Lincopia, where their byſhops ſea is: Halladia, Smalandia, Tniſchia, Verindia, Blechingia, al Dukedomes. Viſby a City of the Gothes, wher was wont to be their auncient &amp; famous Mart,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tes.</note> but now (by the often incurſions &amp; afflictions of the Denmarke and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcouite Pirates) it is depopulated and left deſarte. The ruined monuments do yet apeare, bearing wytnes of the flori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing eſtate of the place. Here was the fyrſte certaine abiding &amp; building of the Gothes, the whyche the Meotides dyd occupy. There is at this preſent daye a goodly Caſtel &amp; a Moneſtary, wherin is a brotherhod of the order of Saynt Benedic,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hauynge a Librarye of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000.</hi> Anethors, &amp; old auncient Hiſtories. Out of thys Countrye, and other the Northeaſt Regions doth come the rytch furres of noble Beaſtes, &amp; chiefelye the coſtlye Sabels, which are wonderfullye eſtemed. They neuer hunt them, but in the Wynter, for then Nature makes their furre thickeſt and ſureſt. They haue an Ilande en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with the Sea,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> reported to be in length. <hi>28.</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne myles, it is greatlye adorned wyth fruitfulnes, for hys fertillitie and plentiful abounding of al thinges, it is called the Mother or noriſher of Swecia.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Of the auncient Kynges of the Gothes &amp; Swecians, after the aucthority of Iohn Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Archbiſhop of Vpſalen.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>gog nephew to Iaphet Noes ſonne (as wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth Ioſeph in his firſte booke of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the. <hi>11.</hi> chapter) was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the Scithians, &amp; was the firſte that raygned kyng among the Scithians in that part of Europ, that
<pb facs="tcp:13623:6"/>now is called Finland. This Magog had. <hi>5.</hi> ſonnes, the eldeſt called Swenus,<note place="margin">Magogs. Sonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> from whom the Swecians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cefued fyrſt their proper name. He ſucceded his father in the kyngdome. And after him his ſecond brother named Gother &amp; of ſom Gog, raigned king. After Gother Vbbo the third ſonne of Magog was elected kyng whoſe ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne was after the flud <hi>.246.</hi> yeres. Thys Vbbo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tyme of Abraham, dyd build the city of Vpſalen which now is their Metrapolitan ſeat,<note place="margin">Vbo bylded Vpſalen, be for the tyme of Abraham</note> he dyed and was buryed in the ſame City. After whoſe death Siggo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned to the kyngdome, and ruled wyth muche honour the terme of <hi>.65.</hi> yeres, geuyng place to nature the <hi>.402.</hi> yere after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floud was buryed at Vpſalen. Whylſt Sig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go raygned in Swecia,<note place="margin">The vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the fyrſt Eric.</note> Eric the fyrſt was choſen Kyng in Gothia: he gouerned with ſo muche Iuſtice as anye prince the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght do, he made lawes &amp; decrees, ſuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world then beſt myght beare. Vertue did ſo gouern hys kyngly aucthority, that many hiſtories report him to be,<note place="margin">Theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes onelye remayne, Vddo, Alo, Othe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gother, Siggo.</note> not onely the chiefe &amp; worthieſt, but alſo the fyrſt king of the Gothes, and the Swecians, he dyed after the floud <hi>425.</hi> From hym to Berico, onelye the names of theyr kynges remayn, as Vddo, Alo, Othen, Charles, Biorno Gother, &amp; Siggo.</p>
               <p>Berico by the common conſent both of the Swecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and Gothes dyd enter into the Monarchy of both kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,<note place="margin">Berico the <hi>14.</hi> kynge, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte that led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye.</note> after the floud <hi>.836.</hi> he was the <hi>.14.</hi> kyng and the firſt that led them out of theyr Country. They departed out of Gothland &amp; Swedland, from the creation of the world <hi>.2831.</hi> and after the floud <hi>.875.</hi> &amp; before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt <hi>.1430.</hi> at what tyme Othoniel iudged Iſraell. This Berico left the crowne to hys ſonne Humulfus, geuing him therwithal a fatherly charge for the wel go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning
<pb facs="tcp:13623:7"/>of his Country. After hym raygned Humelus, couſyn to Humulfus, vnder whom the Danes rebelled, which the Saxons ſeing,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> inuaded Denmarke, wherby they were compelled of neceſſity to yelde &amp; ſubmit them ſelues againe to Humelus. After whoſe death his ſonne Gothilas ſucceded, he raygned with no leſſe valiant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es then did hys father, he dyed &amp; lefte the crowue to Sich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truge.</p>
               <p>Thus farre by the aucthority of Iohn Magnus, Archbiſhop of Vpſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with others: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after foloweth Sebaſtian Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, whoſe aucthority I haue chiefely folowed.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:13623:7"/>
            <head>¶ The antiquitie / the doynges, the encreaſe, and the rytches, wyth the naturall ſituacion of the moſt floriſhyng and lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Country of all the Northeaſt Regions, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sweonia or Swecia, &amp; as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Swedia.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Wecia hath lying vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his weſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the Gothes, vpon the North the Wermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanes, wyth the Scricfins, on the Eaſt, Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ruſſia, and vpon the Southe, the ſea Balthicke. Thys country doth yelde his greateſt aboundaunce of al fruites towardes the North, where the earth beſtoweth her noriſhing giftes of kinde plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully. And alſo there is gathered muche ſtore of honye, very ritche of Syluer, Bras, Leade, Iron, and Cattell.<note place="margin">Rytche of Syluer and other met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.</note> They haue lykewiſe all kinde of fyſhe, which is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receaued of the Sea, but alſo generallye of theyr Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and Pooles. And for Beaſtes to hunt bothe wylde and tame, eyther for pleaſure or profite, no countrye can haue more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Swedia dothe excell Norway.</note>Swecia, as it is wel knowen in largenes, people, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and al other thinges, doth twiſe excel the kingdome of Norway: yet there be in many places, hils ſo ſharpe &amp; hye, and Maraſis ſo deepe and watry, that they are not paſſable, neyther wyth Norſe nor Chariot.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Stockholm their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> City.</note>Their Imperial City is named Stockholme, not ſo byg in quantity, as it is wel fenced and furniſhed, bothe by Nature and Arte. It ſtandeth in a Mariſh grounde, much lyke the cituaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Venis, from whence he taketh his name. For although it be builded in water: yet is the
<pb facs="tcp:13623:8"/>foundacion very ſtrong &amp; ſure. The ſea entreth into it by two great and large armes, that any ſhyp ful fraited, may ſayle with her burden into eyther of them.</p>
            <p>After the incarnacion of Chriſt. <hi>1307.</hi> this city was wonderfullye afflicted,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard of</note> and almoſt vtterly ruined, by a fyre that fell from heauen. For when the lyghtnyng had taken hold of the houſes: it miſerably burnt &amp; broyled as well the people, as their goodes. There periſhed in this pitifull flame. xvi. hundred men. But moſte part of the wemen, with an innumerable ſort of maydes, conueyed them ſelues with their ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; children abourd ſuch ſhyps as lay in their hauens, &amp; with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not a few men. Notwythſtandyng,<note place="margin">A thouſand and ſyx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ndred menne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> before they could depart, the whole multitude (fleing from the peryl of preſent death) vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently imbarked them ſelues with the reſt, &amp; hauing no regard to their common calamity, dyd ouer charge theyr ſhyps, in ſuch ſort that the waters deuoured them both. Such as wyth great hope &amp; haſard,<note place="margin">A wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and a la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ntable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haunce.</note> eſcaped the hatefull death of burning: here ended their lyues with the vnluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky chaunce of drowning. (An example to the worlde, no les worthy to be noted, then it is of al men to be pitied.)</p>
            <p>Thys country of Swecia is ful of Marchandriſe for ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, &amp; for their own neceſſaries, they haue inough to make exchaunge with others. They haue alſo great ſtore of precious furres &amp; mettals. The hye Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines of Norway &amp; Denmarke, are playnly and perfecly ſene of them.<note place="margin">A greate Kynd of cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note> It is for a trothe reported, that the inhabitants of Swecia, haue a wonderful kinde of curtyſe entertain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment wyth them: For they account hym an euyl &amp; naugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye man, that denyeth to the ſtraunger lodgyng, ſo that contencion &amp; ſtrife doth often chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce among them, who Wall firſt receaue the traueler into hys houſe. Where as
<pb facs="tcp:13623:8"/>they pay neither for meate nor drinke. And beſides this,<note place="margin">In Swed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueler p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieth not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vytails, but in corporate townes.</note> they wyll guyde their Geſt to hys next bayght, lendyng hym horſe and other neceſſaries, for the quicker diſpatch of hys iourney. (What greater honour can one do to his country, then in vſyng a ſtraunger friendly?)</p>
            <p>The people of Swecia are many, of ſtrength &amp; armes mighty, both on horſebacke &amp; a foote. In battel bold and valiant, eyther on the land or the ſea. The Dukedome of Angermani, conteineth the North partes, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of Laponie, whoſe country is full of great woods, and large Foreſtes, where their chiefe wylde beaſtes are hunted. The Dukedome of Midelpathus, occupieth the ſouth of Angermani, after whom lyeth the Dukedomes of Helſingia, Geſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritia, Firingia, &amp; Vpſalia their Metra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>politane city, the Dukedome of Coperdalia, where ther is a valley that groweth ful of Copper,<note place="margin">A valley y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> groweth ful of Coppet.</note> alſo Dalecarlia a people ſtrong &amp; mighty in armes. The Dukedome of Vplandia, which hath all hys Countrye with mynes of Siluer, Copper, &amp; Steele.<note place="margin">Vplandia rytche of al mettals.</note> They haue a notable city cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Nicopia, ſtrongly fortified wyth hye walles, &amp; great Bulwarkes. Kolinolnemus deuideth Swecia from Gothelande, by the Poole that ſtretcheth out a longe from Nicopia.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Of the Kynges of Swecia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſeeke the fyrſt ſpryng and originall of the Swecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, my labour ſhould be no les ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an endles trauel, &amp; I thinke it as vn poſſible for others to finde, as myſelfe, both for others to finde, as my ſelfe, both for the antiquiti of their name, and alſo the auncient ſtate &amp; continuaunce of their raigne. Notwyth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding that whych paſſed tyme hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, to the
<pb facs="tcp:13623:9"/>report of letters (which of al auctorities is accounted ol beſt) I haue here briefly collected.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> lande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Long time paſt and long before the natiuity of Chriſt, Sichtrug (as ſaithe Saxus Gramaticus) reigned kyng of Swecia, tyl ſuch time as Gram kyng of Denmarke dyd ouercome and kyl Sichtrug in battel, whereby the Swecians were made for a whyle ſubiectes to the Danes. Then Swiddager kyng of Norway expulſed and draue fourthe Grame bothe out of Denmarke and Swecia,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> by whyche meanes he brought all three kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes vnder one crowne. Suche alteracion and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes of Princes, as our Elders haue ſeene them, ſo we in our daies haue felt the profe of them. For when for tune is diſpoſed to daly with Princes,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſhe maketh theyr ſeat ſo much the hygher, that theyr fall in the ende maye be the greater.</p>
               <p>After Swiddager ſucceeded hys ſonne Haſmond, in the kyngdomes of Swecia &amp; Norway. Vffo after Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, and Hindin after Vffo, Hynding ſucceded Hindin and after his death he left the crowne of Swecia to his ſonne Hothrod. Who, whilſt he ſtriued to amplefy &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large hys kyngdome: loſt both it &amp; hys lyfe. Whereby a way was made for the Danes to the crowne of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. But Atiſle &amp; Nother, the ſonnes of Hothrod, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the ſtraight tribute of the Danes, recouered (&amp; for a ſmall tyme enioyed) the crowne after their Fathers death. For Rolfe, kyng of Denmarke inuaded Swecia, and ſlew Atiſſe in battel. He tooke the Regall name of a king from them, and would in no wiſe haue them beare any Princely dignitye, but to remayne ſubiectes onely to the crowne of Denmarke. Tyll ſuch tyme as Hiartur (a noble man borne of Swecia) dyd ſo enter into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:13623:9"/>and grace of Rolfe,<note place="margin">Swecia is made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that he graunted them the title of a Lieftenant, appointing therwithal a yerely tribute to be payd. And becauſe he wold be the more aſſured of hys fidelity, he gaue hym his ſyſter in mariage.</p>
               <p>The ieſtes &amp; doynges of Swecia remayned in thys ſtate but a whyle: For Hiartur dyd cut of the heade of Rolfe, &amp; he againe of the Danes was polde by the ſame Barber. Then Mother the brother of Atiſſe (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rolfe dyd kyll) ſeyng the Regall ſeate voyde of a kyng, dyd wyn the Nobilities fauour ſo muche, that they poſſeſt him wyth the ſame: and alſo they made it eaſye for hym to brynge in ſubiection the kyngdome of Denmarke,<note place="margin">Denmarke ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowne of Swecia.</note> whych he dyd. But as wyth ſmall trauel &amp; lytle tyme he obtayned it: ſo wyth inconſtancy, and lightnes of minde in les whyle he loſt it. For Baldar dyd driue hym out of Denmarke. Not long after Mother was ſlayn in battel, where vpon the Nobility beyng weary, &amp; loathyng the yoke of the Danes, dyd make Atiſſe (one of the bloude Royal) kyng. Thus paſſed their ſtate for a tyme, wher in no notable thyng is founde to be done amonge the Swecians, wether the Danes to them, or they to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes were ſubiectes. But as by hiſtories it is certaynlye knowen, that aboute the time of Auguſtus Ceſar, Alric was kinge of Swecia, who was ſlayne by Eric, a man of wyt excellent, of toung eloquent, &amp; of handes ready &amp; valiaunt, who vanquiſhed Alric, and raygned kynge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hym. Thys was the ſame tyme, that Chriſte deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from heauen, &amp; tooke vpon hym our mortal nature.<note place="margin">At <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tyme Chriſt deſcended oute of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen.</note> Haldan the ſonne of Eric ſucceeded hys father in the kyndome of Swecia, who was ſlayne, and hys ſonne Siward as heyre to his father, poſſeſt the crown. Then Eric the ſonne of Siwardes doughter and the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:13623:10"/>Froto kyng of Denmarke dyd both ſtep in for the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">Betwene. <hi>2.</hi> ſtooles, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>le goeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ground</note> but they ended theyr raygne by mutual battell, &amp; Haldane the ſecond did get into the Regall ſeate, a man onely geuen to the warres, regarding neither the mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of wyfe, nor the gettyng of chyldren, eſteming more the field conqueſt, then the bed victory, rather delighting in the bloudy dedes of Mars, then in the pleaſaunt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes of Venus, not wythſtandyng he apoynted who ſhould weare the crowne after hym, which was Vngul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. He dyed &amp; left both Swecia and Denmarke, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the gouernment of his ſonne Siwald. After whom Reignold, and after Reignold Aluer, one of the nobleſt men in Swecia ſucceſſiuely raygned kynges. Then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus the eldeſt of Aluers three ſonnes dyd lawfullye ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede hys father.<note place="margin">The kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwen thee bretbre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> But he deuidyng the Realme wyth hys brethren Olaue and Ingellus, did onely reſerue to him ſelfe the general decree of al lawes. He was ſlayne with his brother Olaue in the Denmarke warres, &amp; Ingel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus by the victors conſent enioyed the whole kingdome. Ringus beyng yet but a chylde, dyd raygne after hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ingellus, and after hym Gotare, who was ſlayne in battell agaynſte the Danes, whereby the crowne of Swecia came to Iarmeric kyng of Denmarke.</p>
               <p>Thys was aboute the yeare of Chriſte. <hi>380.</hi> at what tyme the Gothes, that longe before were gone oute of Swecia and Gothia, made great ſpoyle, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully troubled the Romaynes both in Italye, Spayne, and Fraunce. The Gothes which continually remained in theyr countrye, dyd vnit and knyt them ſelues to the Swecians, bothe in lawes and maners, and euer ſynce haue bene ſubiectes to the Kynges of Swecia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:13623:10"/>
               <head>¶Who were Kynges of Swecia, after Charles the great.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the yearely hiſtories and actes of Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia, from Iameric to Fro, is vnknowen to me: I am compelled to let ſlyp and ouer leape that tyme. Fro was kyng of Swecia when Lodowic the ſonne of Charles the great,<note place="margin">Fro kyngs of Swedia was ſlayns by the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>way.</note> dyd ſyt in the Imperial ſeat of Rome. Thys fro was ſlayne by the wemen of Norway. And Herot choſen kyng in hys place which left the ſucceſſion to Sorle, whom Regner kyng of Denmarke ouercame in battell, whereby the crowne came to Biorne the eldeſt ſonne of Regner, who after the trauel of a few yeares in Swecia, gaue place to For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune. For Vnichſert the ſecond ſonne of Regner was cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen kyng for hys brother. And after hym Eric the thirde ſonne of Regner was apoynted to raygne in Swecia.</p>
               <p>But Often a man nobly borne of the bloud royall of Swecia, did oppres and ouerthrow Eric, and tooke the gouernement and rule of hys natiue countrye into hys own handes. Now the brethren of Eric, both to reuenge his death, and alſo to get their old regiment, did ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vexe the kyngdome of Oſten, that they brought the crowne to Sturbiorne Kynge Biorns ſonne, wyth whom Fortune dalyed but a whyle, for he was lykewiſe ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med and driuen out of Swecia,<note place="margin">Olaue the firſt kyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profeſſed Chriſte i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Swedia, was chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned Iames, the yeare of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> by Eric ſonne to Olaue, &amp; couſin to Regner. This man enioyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown wythout any let, trouble, or daunger, who left the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his ſonne Olaue, which quietly poſſeſt the ſame and was the firſt among the Swecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyngs that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed Chriſt. He receyued the holye ſacrament of Baptiſme, and was named Iames.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13623:11"/>
               <p>There were manye in Swecia that longe before hys time did ſecretly profeſſe the faith, and tooke vpon them the holye order of Anſcharius. Thys was the yeare of Chriſt. <hi>1000</hi> at ſuch time as holy Hary was Emperour of Rome.</p>
               <p>After Iames his brother Emonde (borne of a harlot) &amp; a Chriſtian onely in name, dyd ſuccede to the crowne, a man in marcial affaires nothing fortunate. He left the kyngdome to Stinkell, a very good Prince (better worthy of the place, then his predeceſſor) for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion dyd greatlye increaſe in hys tyme. He pulde downe &amp; baniſhed the Idolatry, that the Vpſalieus did vſe, whereby he much honoured his country. &amp; wan him ſelfe a fame perpeiuallye. He alſo appointed the ſame place to be their Metrapolitane City.</p>
               <p>About the yeare of Chriſt. <hi>1100.</hi> he yelded to nature her due,<note place="margin">What two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riueth for, the third en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th.</note> after whoſe deathe, twoo Erics not wythout great ſlaughter &amp; effucion of noble bloude, contended for the crowne. But Halſten ſonne of kyng Stinkell, vpon the vnlucky end of both theſe Erics (who periſhed in battel) as lawful heire poſſeſt the kyngdome, from whence he was by rebellion driuen out agayne, &amp; Animander cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen kyng in hys place. Who for hys crueltye to religion, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in a lytle while after was compeld to treade the ſteps of hys predeceſſor, &amp; Aquine elected kyng in hys roume.</p>
               <p>Then Magnus the ſonne of Nicholas kyng of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke (by the helpe of the Gothes, whych were wearye wyth their often chaunge in Swecia) was made kyng.<note place="margin">The Goth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> deuided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>om the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wedians.</note> The Gothes deuiding them ſelues once more from the body of Swecia, and gaping for an alteracion, dyd truſt that the Imperiall Crowne ſhoulde chaunce to hym, whom they would aſſigne it to. The Swecians (beyng
<pb facs="tcp:13623:11"/>valiant of mynde) would not beare ſo great an iniurye, that their old &amp; auncient cuſtome of choſyng their prince ſhould be by any aſtred. Wherfore they determined that their king ſhould be elected and appointed at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They aduaunſed to the crowne one of their owne countrey, and not onely not regarded, but alſo deſpired the kyng which the Gothes had made.</p>
               <p>The Gothes ſtubburnly and rebelliouſly reſiſting the decree and ſentence of the Swecians, dyd make ciuyll warres agaynſt their newe kyng, whom they dyd ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. And becauſe they would haue Magnus to raigne (which was of the Gothes election) they made the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall ſeate voyde of a Ruler. The Swecians anoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding domeſtical diſcencion, &amp; internal hatred, did condiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend and agre wyth the Gothes (not by compulſion,<note place="margin">The Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>the of ciuyll wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ris.</note> but by requeſt) that Magnus ſhoulde be kyng. After whoſe death, they generallye exalted Swercone to the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Who left a ſonne named Charles, that quietlye &amp; peaceably ſucceded his father, al the tyme of Waldimar kyng of Denmarke, to whoſe doughter he was maried.</p>
               <p>After Charles reigned Eric, who quietlye paſſed hys lyfe with the Danes, &amp; was about the tyme of Chriſte <hi>1249.</hi> Whoſe fate &amp; fortune beyng at an ende, they made great variaunce &amp; diſcord with the kyng Birgerius. He left the kyngdome to Waldimare, who takyng his viage into the holy land, did leaue the protection of his realme to his brother Magnus, which with vnnatural rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did vſurpe the ſame, &amp; would neuer ſurrender it againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aie of a prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Birgerius ſucceded Magnus and tragecally enioyed the crowne. For when he thought him ſelfe moſt aſſured and in the type of al hys glory: he was depriued by Eric his brother, &amp; caſt into the wretched bandes of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:13623:12"/>From whence at length, being by good fortune de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuered, he ioyned his ſonne Magnus quopartner with him in his raigne. Birgerius now at libertie, &amp; knitting amalicious reuenge with his auctoritie, did cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the ſpiteful wrongs he had ſuffred at the handes of his brethren. His vnquenchable colour kynled ſo faſt for repaying the like euyll, that he would by no meanes be pacified, til that with their bloud he was ſatiſfied.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall murder among bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note>When hys brethren leaſt feared hym, and when they thought the ſtinking miſt of al malice to be voide, then did he with a tained coulour of frendſhyp requeſt them to a banquet, where in the myddeſt of their mirth, they were cruelly ſlaine. This horrible &amp; deteſtable fact dyd ſo creepe into the eares of the Commons, that it moued euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the iuſt reuengement of ſo murdriſh a dede.</p>
               <p>Then he with his Quene fled, &amp; left his ſonne Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus behinde him: whoſe heade reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſed the offence of his father. After who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they aduaunced Magnus the ſon of Eric (which was behedded at his brothers banquet) to the imperial crowne. His raigne was ſo proſperous, that with the help of vertue, and the fauour of good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,<note place="margin">The kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way knyt to the crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</note> he ioyned the country of Norway to his kingdom of Swecia, &amp; was crowned king of both countries. He yelded Nature her due the yeare of Chriſt. <hi>1326.</hi> and left a ſonne called Magnus, heire to bothe the kyngdomes. Magnus did promis the mariage of his ſonne Aquine to the natural ſiſter of the Earle of Holſt, on this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that if Aquine receiued her not a Maide, al the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men and rulers of Swecia, ſhoulde be free of theyr othe and alegeaunce to the King. This Maide ſaylinge into Swecia, was taken vpon the ſea of Waldimar, King of Denmarke, &amp; Margaret, Waldimars doughter
<pb facs="tcp:13623:12"/>was maried to Aquine: Which thyng the Gouernours of Swecia perceiuyng, denyed their duty &amp; homage to their Prince (becauſe he kept not promiſe with them) &amp; forthwith they were ſent of the Earle of Holſt to Albert Duke of Magnopolis, father in law to the ſayd Earle: who had maried Eufemia the kings ſiſter, whoſe ſonne named Albert, they would haue to their king, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued Magnus from al his royall dignitie.</p>
               <p>But he ſeing him ſelfe depoſed &amp; forſaken, dyd ioyne with Aquine to make cruel war againſt Albert, whoſe force nought auailed, for Alberts power was more able to reſiſt them, then theirs was to ouerthrow him.<note place="margin">Magnus of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuexyle.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Magnus was compelled in the ende, to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his baniſhment, wherein he dyed.</p>
               <p>Albert being now eſtabliſhed, and with princely auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority confirmed in his kingdome: did apoint hymſelfe with al honourable furniture, ſyt for a King, &amp; leauing the charge of the regall gouernement, in the handes of Diſmarie, did ſayle to his Countrey Magnopolus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The valya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and haught mynde of a woman.</note>In the meane ſeaſon whilſt theſe thinges were a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Margaret the doughter of Waldimar king of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke &amp; Norway, after the death of her huſbande, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected the two kingdomes with her litle ſonne Olaue. And hauing a deſire to the regiment of Swecia, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to quarel with Albert, king of the ſame. They both leuied two mighty armies, &amp; committing the ſucceſſe of their good or euyl fortune, to the bloudy lot of war, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert (who hadde finiſhed the courſe of hys proſperous raygne) was wyth his yonge ſonne Eric, of Margaret taken priſoners, with whom they were kept in miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble captiuitye, the lyngring tyme of ſeuen yeares.<note place="margin">Margar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Queene of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> three kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</note> By which ouerthrowe of Albert, the thre kyngdomes were
<pb facs="tcp:13623:13"/>once more ſubiectes to one crowne, and haue alwayes remained ſo euer ſince. The Norwaiſe neuer chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging nor diſagreing: but the Swecians refuſing to beare the troubleſome yoke of a ſtraunger, haue often tymes ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the ſocietie of the Danes.</p>
               <p>Now Albert vpon this condicion was deliuered oute of myſon, that he ſhould within three yeares folowyng, pay three ſcore thouſand marke, or els deliuer the town and Caſtel of Stockholme, otherwyſe to be impriſoned againe, Albert would haue ſurrendred the City, but the Swecians would not by any meanes agree to it, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therfore in diſpaire, and voyde of all hope of recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hys kyngdome, dyd geue vp al, and contented hym ſelfe wyth his old Magnopolus.</p>
               <p>The mightye Margaret triumphantlye raygnynge Quene of the three kingdomes, paſſed her youthe wyth great pompe among the Swecians, tyll ſuche tyme as crooked age, with creping pace ouertoke her (whoſe ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſteps none can ouer runne) and then by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon counſel and conſent of her rulers and gouernours, ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted Eric Captaine of Pomeranie to her ſonne.<note place="margin">The Capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meranye is made kyng. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this Phillipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngs dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land.</note> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſe death he was made Kyng of the three kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, &amp; quietly paſſed his tyme a great while amonge the Swecians. For Philippa the Quene his wife, and daughter to the kyng of Portugal, dyd moſt commonly lye in Swecia, where in the end ſhe dyed.</p>
               <p>Now the kyng hauing continual warres, &amp; wantyng money, dyd (contrary to his othe) ſpoile the Swecians, and ſought al the meanes he myght to impoueriſhe the country, becauſe it ſemed welthiar &amp; much more rytcher then the reſt. Which made the Nobilitie to declare their impacience with open enuy (for the Swecians, as they
<pb facs="tcp:13623:13"/>are ſlow to conceiue a wrong: ſo are they quicke in the reuenge of iniurie) but when this was reported, and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectly related to the Earles of Eric, he which for his euil eſtemed nothing, litle regarded it.<note place="margin">The ſmal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gard of prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tymes cauſe of their more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtruction.</note> Tyll ſuche tyme as Engelbert (a noble man both by birth &amp; condicion) dyd rayſe rebellion againſt him. And where as he had torti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Caſtels and fortes of Swecia with captaines &amp; officers of the Danes: Thys Engelbert remoued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and did conſtitute &amp; apoint Swecians in their places.</p>
               <p>Then Eric at the firſt wyth great expedicion, ſought to feare Engelbert wyth cruell threatnynges, whyche nought auailed, for his magnanimity was able to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpaiſe the others enuy. Wherefore he rayſed a mighty army, thinkyng thereby to pacefy the Swecians furye. He ſaylinge with hys parnicious companye towardes Swecia, was preuented of his purpoſe by a terrible tempeſt, wherin moſt of them were drowned. And Eric him ſelfe compeld to land with a few, where he ſawe by experience that fauour and not force, wold vanquiſh the Swecians. Althinges chauncing contrary to his expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, he dyd wyth muche ſpeede and lyttle gayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into Denmarke.</p>
               <p>At length the Portes &amp; townes adioyning to the ſea, made this concord &amp; agrement betwene Eric and Engel bert: Eric ſhuld be king on this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion,<note place="margin">A kyng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> condicions.</note> that no Danes but Swecians ſhould beare office in their holdes, their Cities ſhoulde keepe their olde liberties, and their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes their accuſtomed fraunches. The kyng beyng reſident in the country, ſhould receiue hys whole reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe, and beyng abſent, but the one halfe.</p>
               <p>Theſe thynges agreed vpon, he ſaild into Denmarke, where the Danes takynge example of the Swecians,
<pb facs="tcp:13623:14"/>preſcribed certayne rules and orders, which they would haue compelled their kyng to folow, wherby much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble happened in their country. He therwithall wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully offended,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oke hys kyngdome.</note> did gather together as much treaſure as he might. And ſwearing neuer more to medle wyth the troubleſome ſtate of a kyng, dyd ſayle into Pruſſia.</p>
               <p>After whom Chriſtopher Prince of Palatine, &amp; Duke of Bauar, conſin to Eries ſiſter, was generallye choſen by the chiefe Rulers of the three kingdomes. Whereby they thought to haue prouided a great tranquilitie and quietnes to their Marchauntes. This man altered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng in Swecia, tyl ſuch tyme as (not contented with his owne proſperitye) he began to enuy their countrye. And then he heaped vp al the treaſure of the kingdome, as wel that which was gathered of many yeres before: as his own, and ſent it away by the ſea.</p>
               <p>After whoſe death the Swecians would ioyne their kingdome no more with the Danes,<note place="margin">The Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians refuſe to be knyt wyth the Danes.</note> but with a muche better wyl dyd chuſe to their kyng Charles Canutus, one of their owne, a worthy Ientleman, &amp; nobly borne, of the old &amp; auncient bloud of the kinges of Gothea and Swecia. He ſcant had finiſhed .vii. yeares in his raigne, when he began to ware very greuous &amp; couetous in all thinges,<note place="margin">Peruers counſel bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temple to the Prince.</note> altring his noble nature, from vpright Iuſtice, to ſeuere &amp; cruel puniſhment, accounting his wyl in eche decree to be a law, which cauſed hys faythfull &amp; louyng ſubiectes to reuolt and turne from hym. When he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that they ſweld ſo agaynſt hym, ſuche thinges as he had before his election, he gathered together, and pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing the treaſure of the crowne in a ſure hold, imbarked him ſelfe and went to Gedamus. When the kyng was croſſe ſaild, and wanting nothing for hys departure, but
<pb facs="tcp:13623:14"/>onely waying of Ancker: one of his noble men demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of hym it he had not left ſomething a ſhore vndone,<note place="margin">This is not ſounde in Mounſter, but ye ſhall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thes.</note> whych he would haue executed. To whom the Kyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a great ſygh anſwered: Yes verelye, I haue neglected longe tyme ſynce, the executyng of thee and thy lyke, which yf I had then done, I had nowe quietlye remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the common wealth.</p>
               <p>Then Chriſtiern (whom the Danes and Norwayſe had elected for their Kyng) was called into the kingdom to be crowned, whereby the thre kyngly titles did ioyne agayne in one. Not long after, the Swecians did moue iuſt rebellion agaynſt kyng Chriſtiern, becauſe he kepte not promiſe with them, nor did not wiſely obſerue thoſe thinges he had taken in hand. The kyng therfore the <hi>.7.</hi> yeare of his raygne, &amp; the yeare of Chriſt <hi>.1469.</hi> dyd enter with cruel battel into the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of Swecia, wher as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitantes being knit together, did eaſely reſiſt him. Notwithſtanding thys repulſe, he had <hi>.2.</hi> Caſtels in the Country, that wonderfully vexed &amp; troubled the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians. Afterwarde the Kyng entryng agayne wyth an army into Swecia: could doo no good for hym ſelfe, nor damage to his enemye, for the ſtrayghte paſſage of the mountaynes. In the meane ſeaſon Charles Canutus that was Kyng of Swecia, dyed: in whoſe place they choſe Steno, one of theyr worthy Captaynes,<note place="margin">The Sweci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans chuſe Steno to be gouernour, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thef giue the auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye of a kynge, but not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name.</note> to whom they gaue the authority of a Kyng, but not the name. He myght call &amp; commaund all the Swecian Princes and Rulers to anye affayres about the Realme: ſuche one whom the Germaynes name a Marſhal, the Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Conſtable, &amp; the Romaynes a Mayſter of the Horſe. In great reuerence and eſtimacion was thy Steno, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Swecians. For they accounted hym as well
<pb facs="tcp:13623:15"/>worthy of the crowne, as any of his predeceſſors, which they not ſeldom tymes offered hym, wyth the name of a Kyng, but he continually refuſed it. Iohn the ſonne of Chriſtiern,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn kyng of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> gape for the crowne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ecia.</note> beyng placed ſucceſſor in both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdomes of Demnarke &amp; Norway, dyd alſo gape for the crowne of Swecia. Whoſe expectacion they lykewiſe had ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, if he would haue bene bound (as the reſt of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors were) to the obſeruances of al their old lawes and cuſtomes, whych he refuſed, vnles he myght haue it wyth the franke auctority of a Prince.</p>
               <p>Many yeares paſſed whilſt the affayres of Swecia, remayned in thys ſtate, and chiefe lye becauſe theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector was of ſuch Iuſtice, that the people had no deſyre to a Kyng. Now Iohn the ſonne of Chriſtiern, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng together an excedyng great and myghty army,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn kyng of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mark dothe van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyſh Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia.</note> did lead them into Swecia: Where after many bloudy bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tels, he conquered the Country. Not long after, when the Kyng was buſyed about the determinacions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntmentes of hys doynges, ther roſe a rumir among the people, how eaſely they myght recouer theyr liberty: The kyng beyng ſo buſely occupyed aboute the eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of his own eſtate. But he perceiuyng theyr mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muryng myndes, dyd leaue hys wyfe wyth a Garyſon in the Caſtel of Stockholme, &amp; priuely departed out of the Country. The Quene thus left, the Swecians did beſiege the Caſtel,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ng Tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt .<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. yere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſte.</note> wherein ſhe was, &amp; at lengthe by the extremity of famyne &amp; hungar ſhe yelded, and went to the Monaſtery of ſaynt Brydget, from whence ſhe was after the ſpace almoſt of two yeares delyuered by Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Legat of Rome. In the meane tyme kyng Iohn dyd leny a huge army, to cary into Swecia, where he hauyng many friendes whych ſent hym word eyther to
<pb facs="tcp:13623:15"/>bryng fifty thouſand men, or els his trauel ſhould be in vayne. Notwithſtandinge he attempted thys warre,<note place="margin">Fyfty thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand Danes go into ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle not.</note> wherein he litle preuayled, hauing his ſonne Chriſtiern a ſoldiour wyth hym. After the trauel of a ſmal tyme in theſe doutful doynges, he dyed, and lefte Chriſtiern hys ſonne in hys place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The tragicall hyſtorye, and tiranicall doynges of the ſecond Chriſtiern king of Denmarke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtiern the ſecond, king of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marke, &amp; ſon to Iohn, dyd plainly demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate in his youth where vnto he would be chiefely addicted in his age. For beyng a ſoldiour vnder his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Swecian warres, he vſed hym ſelfe verye fierce and cruel, &amp; in peace at home double &amp; deceitfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtiern kyng of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>marke doth enterpriſe to inuade Swedia.</note>This Chriſtiern ful fraighted with ambicion, &amp; as it ſhould ſeme naturally enclined to miſchiefe, began im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after hys fathers death wyth haught mynde to make ciuil warres, and firſt he enterpriſed to inuade Swecia. But when he perceiued them to be of ſuche great myght, that as long as there was no domeſticall diſcencion nor vnnaturall hatred betwene them, they could wel defend their country nerehand, &amp; alſo ſubdue their enemy abroade: He practiſed to get that by polecy, whych he could not get by force and therfore he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to kyndle contencion, and to ſowe ſedicion amonge the Swedian confederates.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt he procured to this treaſon, Goſtaue the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapolitan Byſhop of Vpſalien. Who by the inſtigacion of Chriſtiern, did not onely condiſcend &amp; agree therunto
<pb facs="tcp:13623:16"/>hym ſelfe, but alſo alured a great nomber more to ioyne wyth hym,<note place="margin">Goſtaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhop of Vpſalien, go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th about to betray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his country</note> whych were fully determined, and certainly apoynted the yere of Chriſt <hi>.1517.</hi> to betray and delyuer theyr country to kyng Chriſtiern. But as ſoone as thys treaſon was related, &amp; perfectly knowen to the ſeconde Steno, generall Gouernour of Swecia: he preſentlye perſwaded and exhorted the Byſhoppe to leaue of hys euyl begun enterpriſe, friendly chargeing hym to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the end before the beginning, and not to take that in hand,<note place="margin">Friendlye admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> which ſhould be the deſtruction of his natiue and natural country, &amp; alſo purchaſe to hym ſelfe an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting infamy. But the biſhop co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temning this fauorable admonicion, dyd with a ſtedfaſt mynde continue in hys trayterous entent, &amp; now ſeing hys diueliſh doinges to be bewrayed,<note place="margin">The byſhop beſieged in the caſtel of Stech.</note> he fled for refuge to the Caſtell of Stech, where in he was by Stenoes ſoldiours beſieged.</p>
               <p>Chriſtiern kyng of Denmarke hearyng of the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that Goſtaue was in, lyke a faythful confederat, did leuy an army for his deliuery, truſting by hys power to ſet the biſhop at liberty, &amp; alſo by his might to vanquiſh the country.<note place="margin">Chriſtiern ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med and dryuen out of Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But he beyng driuen backe &amp; ouerthrowen by the Swecians, was compelled to forſake the reſcue of Goſtaue, and to returne with the loſſe of a great nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of hys men into Denmarke. The Byſhop vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the vnfortunate ſucceſſe of hys companion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng voyde of al hope, &amp; vtterly in diſpay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of al ayd: dyd fayne a repentaunce,<note place="margin">Goſtaue fai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th a repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth yelde.</note> &amp; was contented ſymplye to yelde hym ſelfe, onely the ſiege to be raiſed. It was agred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; the Byſhop thus deliuered (becauſe he would ſeme to be perfect ſory for hys offence) he left hys eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dignity, &amp; priuately lyued of hys own patrimony.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſtiern ſeing the head &amp; chiefe inſtrument of
<pb facs="tcp:13623:16"/>hys confederacye to be vnarmed, whereby the reſt that wer of no ſuch auctority (as the Biſhop) might y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eaſſlyer be diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred: he began to execute his malicious enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> open force,<note place="margin">Chriſtiern the ſeconde tyme bothe inuade ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. Stockholm deſieged.</note> &amp; gathering together a huge &amp; mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty army, dyd leade them into Swecia, fullye bent wyth his monſtrous power to ouer ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the country, &amp; to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the people with cruel ſeruitude. He incamped round about Stockholme, makyng hys fyrſte attempt wyth theyr chiefe &amp; principal Citye. But the Swecian ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours laced hym &amp; his army in ſo ſtraight, that they could get neyther victuel for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues,<note place="margin">The extrem hunger of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Danes.</note> nor forage for theyr horſe, whych cauſed hys hoſte to peryſhe wyth extreme hunger. In thys miſerable eſtate they remayned almoſt two monethes, plaged wyth al euyls &amp; diſcommodities that myght be, and returne into Denmarke they coulde not, the wyndes were ſo aduers agaynſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtiern practiſeth his deliuery by craft.</note>Fleyng therfore to hys old &amp; priuy miſchiefes, he prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the deliuery of hym &amp; his (by craft) from thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, wherein they were wrapped. For beyng thus wyth the ſharpe &amp; gredy plague of famin oueco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med: he deſired truſe, &amp; an end of the wars. Steno (Gouernour of Swecia) wyth glad mynde condiſcended &amp; agreed to the peace.<note place="margin">A treaty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> peace. The noble dede of Ste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no.</note> He alſo conſidering the horryble penury of his aduerſaries, did (vpon a valiant &amp; pityful mynde) ſend in to the campe of the Danes a nomber of Biefes, wyth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther victuel, wherby the paynful hunger of hys enemies was relieued. Chriſtiern faining a great fauour to Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, &amp; fraudulently ſemyng to be muche beholdyng vnto hym, for thys good turne of hys, dyd ſend into the City, requeſtyng hym friendly to come into hys tent, &amp; ſpeake with him.<note place="margin">Steno was voyde of diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yght.</note> The which Steno (who ment all truth) had done, if the Senate of Stockholm had not ſtayed him.
<pb facs="tcp:13623:17"/>For he was ſo noble of mynde, that he thoughte no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite could lurke in a Princes breſt. But the Auncientes of the City, conſideryng their wealth &amp; decay to remain in hys parſon, would not ſuffer him, vpon ſo ſlender an entreaty to depart out of the towne.</p>
               <p>The Dane therfore perceiuyng this euyl to be ſpyed, or at the leaſt fruſtrate:<note place="margin">The Dane deniſeth yet another miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiefe.</note> dyd yet deniſe a nother miſchief, declaring how he would come into the City among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he might haue pledges for his ſafe returne. Steno be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing therto throughlye perſwaded, dyd appoynt certaine yong noble Gentlemen, to be his warrauntes. Among whom was the moſt valiant Goſtaue Erichſon, Father to the noble Eric,<note place="margin">Goſtaue E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>richſon fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Eric nowe kyng of Swedia, to ſent for a pledge to Chriſtiern, who caryed hym pryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marke.</note> now Kyng of Swecia. He wyth the reſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting them ſelues to the fidelity of the Danes, entred into theyr Campe, from whence they were caried to their ſhyps, and there (contrary to the expectacion of Steno) were bound in Irons.</p>
               <p>The king thus falſelying his fayth, dyd not according to his princely promiſe come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> city: but waying his anckers, &amp; hoyſing vp hys ſayles, made ſpeede with hys pray into Denmarke. The Swecians (not without iuſt cauſe) did greatly enuy the infidelitie of the Danes,<note place="margin">Chriſtiern returnes in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mark</note> and alſo deplored &amp; lamented for the loſſe of theſe noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who were by the fraudulent dealynges of Chriſtern, cleane againſt the lawe of armes, forceablye made, not pledges (as appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was) but priſoners, as the Dane would: After this flight, Chriſtiern the ſpace of .iiii. yere was quiet: ſtrengthning his power with men, &amp; enryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his cofers with money, remaining ſtill in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable purpoſe, &amp; diueliſh entent (at tyme conuenient) to ſcourge Swecia with ſome greater plage. Vnto which furious madnes Nature had borne hym, will had fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:13623:17"/>him, &amp; Fortune had apointed him. Leuying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great army, did once more inuade Swecia.<note place="margin">Chriſtiern doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third time inuade Swecia.</note> Leuying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great army, did once more inuade Swecia. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no remembring the Irregal part of Chriſtiern, with an ireful minde of reuenge, did wyth great expedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make haſte to meete him, &amp; fully bent to trye the might of his enemy: did ioyne battail with him. Where Steno play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the part of a noble Captain,<note place="margin">Steno play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the part bothe of a Captayne &amp; a Soldiour was ſlaynt.</note> &amp; alſo of a valiant Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, manfully fighting in the face of his aduerſaries, receuing many &amp; greuous woundes (not without great loſſe to his country) with high laud was ſlaine. After whoſe euerthrow the Swecians for a while did fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintaine the fyght, their bloudye bodies poſſeſſing thoſe places being dead, that thei were apointed to kepe by their captain being alyue. Notwithſtanding the bold &amp; haught courages of the Swecian ſoldiours could not long preuayle, the power of the enemy being ſo great, &amp; not onely their field leader, but alſo their commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth Gouernour being killed. Therfore they were compelled to commit the ſafegarde of their owne lyues to flyght, and like men without a Captaine left the field.</p>
               <p>Goſtaue the counterfait biſhop, vtterly drowned in al miſchiefe, &amp; naturallye enclined to diſceight,<note place="margin">Goſtaue ſhaketh of his diſcemn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citye.</note> cloking his euil &amp; naughty deſire with poore repentaunce, couering his crafty entencion with the cloude &amp; darknes of fained holynes, who ſemed to liue ſolitarely tyll this preſent. Whom no gladnes could reioyce, nor no pleaſure could pleaſe: now ſeing his natural countrye men thus ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed and diſperced, lyke an vnnaturall beaſt with a ioyful minde, did ſhake of his diſcemuled ſimplicity, and vnbrideling the raine of his hipocritical luſt,<note place="margin">Goſtaue to turneth to hyn trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> creping out of his lurking Iuy tree, returned to his trayterous vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met: muche more glorying in the victorye of Chriſtiern,
<pb facs="tcp:13623:18"/>then bewayling the lamentable ouerthrow of hys coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye men.</p>
               <p>The wynning of one fielde was to the kyng no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, nor the loſſe of one battell was to the Swecians no ſubiection. Wherfore he went about once againe to compaſſe with craft his pretenſed purpoſe, &amp; gylefullye determined (vnder the fauourable name of peace) to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute great cruel &amp; incredible euils:<note place="margin">The Senat of Stocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holme at ſo licited to peace.</note> which he could not ſo perfectly bring to paſſe by the force of his army: therfore he ſolicited the Senat of Stockholme to an honeſt and perfect agrement.</p>
               <p>The treatye was broughte to thys ende, that they were contented with any honeſt condicions of peace: ſo that the vncertain and miſerable broile of warre myght ſeace. They ſo muche regarded the quiet eſtate of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitye, that they preferred thys diſceitfull amitye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the aſſuraunce of theyr owne ſafetye. The Aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes and chiefe Rulers of Stockholme dyd preſcribe the Articles which were theſe:<note place="margin">The condici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of peace.</note> Chriſtiern ſhould keepe and mayntaine the lawes and cuſtomes of theyr Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye vnbroken, he ſhoulde not infringe nor take awaye the liberties of their Cities, he ſhoulde forgeue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all ſuche as had woren armour agaynſt hym.</p>
               <p>The Dane (who neuer deſyred quietnes, but to ſome miſcheuous ende) had ſuttellye conceiued all theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in his heade before,<note place="margin">The wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges of peace at bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r men wyth theſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> feales.</note> knowing that this agreement was the path way to hys inhumane purpoſe. He ſwore a ſolempne othe, wrytynges were drawen, both of theyr peace and amitye. Whereunto they dyd ſeuerallye ſet their handes and ſeales.</p>
               <p>The Citizens throughly perſwaded, or rather inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently blinded, by this fraudulent diſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t: laid open their
<pb facs="tcp:13623:18"/>gates to theyr enemies,<note place="margin">The Danes enter into Stockholm</note> &amp; receiued their new reconciled friendes into the City, whereinto many of the Countrye dyd enter wyth them. Not treatyng them ſtraungelye as late aduerſaries, but curteſlye wyth muche gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as auncient friendes, dyd vſe them honourablye.</p>
               <p>Chriſtiern dyd dwel in his miſcheuous diſſimulacion, tyll ſuche tyme as he and hys Soldiours were of their trauelous toyle well refreſhed, and alſo had the Caſtell of Stockholme ſtronglye fortefied wyth his Gariſons, wardes, and watches.<note place="margin">Chriſtiern doth cal the Danes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o horrible co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unſayle.</note> Then longyng and luſtyng for his horrible entencion, and boyling in hys diueliſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, he called the Danes to a Councell, belchyng oute the rancour and poyſoned deuiſe of hys murdriſh mind, for the deſtruction both of the City and Citizens. He aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth their iudgement, howe and by what meanes he anyght beſt deſtroy them, eyther by force or polecye.</p>
               <p>O thriſe vnhappy Citizens, and moſt vnfortunate Swecians, what ment you to laye open your gates for ſuche a Geaſt, whoſe Fame, Fortune, and hyghe feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citye, dyd enlarge hys libertye wyth ſpightfull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Coulde not hys often double dealinges haue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you? Could not the enſample of his firſt breatche of promiſe teache you? Nor would not the ſuretye of your owne perſons ſuffice you, but that you muſt open your bowels, and cut foorthe your entrailes to feede your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies wyth your bloude? Why dyd you not preuent thys dampnable counſell? Was there no Prophet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? Was there no celeſtiall ſygne ſhewed vnto you? Could no Swecian eare be ſo happye to harken to thys conſpiracie?<note place="margin">The bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>k <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen.</note> That whylſt you walke vp and ded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Citye, thynkyng your ſelues in moſte ſecuritye, the bloudy lottes of your lyues be drawne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13623:19"/>
               <p>O cruell Chriſtiern, coulde nothing remoue nor induce thy vicies, to dread the terrible puniſhment of murdriſh mindes? What great and greuous tempeſtes of hatred lurked in thy breſt, that thou muſt needes thus thunder out thy horrible and dampnable ſentence, againſt thoſe that reuerenced thee, regarded thee, and honoured thee? They were become thy ſubiectes, &amp; thou ſhouldeſt haue bene their king. They tooke thee to defende them from forein force: and not to ſpoyl them with cruel ſlaughter. They tooke thee to rule with Iuſtice, and not to raigne with rigour.<note place="margin">The Swedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans tooke Chriſtiern for a king, &amp; not for a kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>let.</note> They choſed thee a king, and not a kyller. They tooke thee a Man, &amp; not a Monſter. How muche diddeſt thou digreſſe from humaine nature, when thou apointedeſt thy ſelfe for an inſtrument of murder? Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was become thy ſences? could no perill feare thee? could no reaſon rule thee? nor could no ſhame withdrawe thee from thy deteſtable entent? Did not thy conſcience wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren thee? Did not the horror of mynde trouble thee? nor did not the ſwift courſe of fame baſhe thee,<note place="margin">Fame flieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at &amp; ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> wyth Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces boi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth Princes doinges to the extreme confines of the world? Was there no good counſeller in this aſſemble? Was there no Dane that durſt diſſwade thee? Haddeſt thou no faithful &amp; free friend in al thy company? not one that loued thee? not one that frankely would refourme thee?<note place="margin">The Danes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drid more their kings fauour, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his honour</note> not one among them al that tendred more thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, then thy fauour? O pityful caſe. Were they all as thy ſelfe minded, and thou as they determined? A mete king for ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelers, &amp; apt ſubiectes for ſuch a Prince.</p>
               <p>Now for this traiterous conſpiracy againſt the Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians, whoſe counſel was moſt woorſt, that was beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, &amp; whoſe tale tended to moſt tirannye, that was beſt lyked. For amonge all their diueliſhe deuiſes thys
<pb facs="tcp:13623:19"/>dampnable ſentence chiefelye pleaſed: That Chriſtiern ſhould appoynt a general triumphe &amp; feaſt for his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion,<note place="margin">The dellyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of their dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uclywe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> whereunto al the Nobility &amp; Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia would repaire, with a great nomber of others. And hauing them once within the Citye, by the coulour of friendly chere &amp; familiar countenaunce, he might the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; with leſſe daunger, ouerthrow &amp; confounde them. Then he might execute that which his beaſtly immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, &amp; importunat nature did driue him to, when as no wiſdome, no power, nor no polecy ſhould redreſſe theyr woful cauſe, ſo ſuddein a miſchief co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnlooked for. The are ſhould lye on their neckes, before they ſhoulde thinke to dye. Their weapons warme in their bloude, before they coulde iudge any harme, and heapes ſhould be murdred, before they ſhould finde the peryl.</p>
               <p>This was thought by the whole conſent &amp; ſocietye of thys facinorous aſſemblye, to be the chiefe and perfecte meane for the vtter decay of the whole countrye. The Kyng alſo greatly aloweth this practiſe,<note place="margin">Chriſtiern burneth for the ſequell of hys ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</note> &amp; burning with an incredible deſire, to accompliſhe &amp; bring to effect thys horrible deuice: he commaundeth the feaſt, he maketh great preparacion, he apointeth the order of the triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe, he geueth honorable entertainment to al the Nobility, lodging moſt part of them in the Caſtel, he prouoketh a myrth, he ſemeth to reioyce, he vſeth al men with a ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng countenaunce friendlye. The Danes ſet out them ſelues in althinges merely, and the Swecians doo the ſame, not knowing that their bloud ſhould pay for their banquet. Three daies continued their good chere, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in there wanted nothing that might force a gladnes.<note place="margin">Three daies continued they: good chere.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But now the doleful fate of the Swecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aproching, and their miſerable &amp; murdriſh tormentes at hande: no
<pb facs="tcp:13623:20"/>one among them al could ſpy the imminent peril of their preſent deſtruction. No hart panted, no fleſh trembled, nor no minde was moued with any mocion of their pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent end.<note place="margin">Chriſtiern thirſteth for the attempt of his tiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye.</note> Chriſtiern (whoſe cruell courage vehementlye thurſted for the attempt of this tiranny) dyd ſende hys Garde into the Caſtel with ſtraight commaundement, violently to bynde &amp; ſpoyle the Swecian Geaſtes (who wer in the middeſt of their banqueting myrth, pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſing the tyme,<note place="margin">The Sweci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans in the myddeſt of their ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ket. The begy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this diuely ſhe myrth.</note> more reioycing in long life, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for preſent death) &amp; to caſt them into Dungeons Now beginneth this fury to heape miſchiefe vpon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, nowe doth he repugne againſt humaine nature, &amp; with an incredible audacitie ſurmounteth hys hellyſhe purpoſe. The day folowing the gates of the towne we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rammed vp, the Lieftenauntes were ſent out to defend ciuyl force, &amp; the Trumpets were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded earlye in the morning to ſound their bloudy &amp; dreadful noyſes. Al the mighty ſoldiours wer apointed to be ready through the City in their armour, with terrible &amp; cruell counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, like wilde and horrible Monſters. That what with the roaring noyſe of the enemy, &amp; the feareful cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of harnis, euery one ſhould more doubt hys owne death, then eyther the loſſe of the Citye, the reſiſtyng of the aduerſary, or the ſafegard of his owne familye. It was alſo apointed,<note place="margin">It was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no place ſhoulde bee voyde of ſlaughter,</note> that what with ſpillyng of bloude &amp; ſlaughter of Citizens, no place, no ſtreete, nor any waye ſhould be voyde of moſt dampnable murther. And that from the Caſtel to the Market place al ſhoulde be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, torne downe, and ruined wyth the warme bloud of the vnfortunate Swecians. Then was there brought from the palace two Byſhops, Scarencis, and Strengenencis, which wer with pulling, halyng, &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:13623:20"/>thruſting amonge a ſorte of tirannicall villaines, brought to the place of execution.<note place="margin">Twoo By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops behed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.</note> There ſtoode an aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare before the counſel houſe: where they being cruellye throwen agaynſt the grounde, loſt their heades. After them the Rulers, chiefe Officers, &amp; Auncientes,<note place="margin">The aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, &amp; chief Officers, at tirannouſly murdred.</note> wyth ſuche as were knowen to haue done any thing boldly in the defence of theyr Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; alſo the Senat of Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holme, men graue, wytty, and wealthy: were al drawen from the Caſtell, &amp; all together were moſt tirannouſlye murdred. Then made they a preſcript table,<note place="margin">A Table made, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in is wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the names of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhoulde be kylled.</note> wherein was written the names of thoſe whom they wold haue ſlayne. With this the Garde ran through the Citye, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutyng theyr deteſtable miſchiefe vpon all thoſe whom they had marked. From the which no man coulde flye, nor hyde him ſelfe, for all places of refuge was ſhut vp. The Danes augmented their monſtrous doinges with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lewd &amp; vngracious actes, both of handes &amp; body. For the Soldiours and common people beynge mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, was cauſe:<note place="margin">A generall ſlaughter.</note> that with vehement violence thei did not onely kyl ſuch as wer apointed, but alſo others that wer but lookers on of ſo cruel a ſpectacle. They ſpared none, they pitied none, nor they regarded none: but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into their houſes, did draw out their vnarmed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and yelding bodies to the ſlaughter. So muche did the diueliſh deſire of hellyſh madnes conquer them, that they executed infinite, curſed, &amp; wycked vengeaunce, as wel agaynſt God as man.<note place="margin">Some Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens bydde them ſelues</note> When as in thys tumult &amp; bloudy broyle, a great nomber of the Citizens had hyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them ſelues in darke &amp; ſecret places: and Chriſtiern perceiuing a many that had not as yet taſted of his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany,<note place="margin">A falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamacion.</note> he cauſed to be proclaimed from the counſel houſe, that al ſuch as liued, &amp; had eſcaped his terrible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<pb facs="tcp:13623:21"/>ſhould remayne vnpunniſhed, &amp; be free with their lines. The good fame and report of this moſt horrible diſceite and falſe lye, ſo crept into the eares of the vnhappy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens (whoſe hartes were wrapped in infinite miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) that wher as they lucked with ſome ſafety in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure &amp; vnknowen coruers, they came abrod and opened them ſelues to their enemies, at whoſe hands they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d neither fauour, grace, nor mercy, but preſent death. For the example of their former tirannies proceded likewiſe vpon theſe: The Garbe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit euery one to the ſword, whoſe bloudy myndes voyde of al pity dyd murther as many as they could fynde, &amp; ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tyl ſuch tyme as al were kylled. The loude clamour of the Danes,<note place="margin">the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tenace of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; the pitiful noyſe of the Matrons (play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with ſhriking cries, for the death of their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds) myngled wyth the hydeous gronynge of the murdred Swecians, was horrible to heare. Al places was fylled wyth armour, carkaſes, bloud, and lamentation.</p>
               <p>Becauſe Chriſtiern would haue his tiranny the more to excel:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al &amp; dete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Uranay.</note> he dyd with great villany &amp; ſpight take a certain noble man, whoſe name was Iohn, &amp; cleaue againſt al lawes, both natural &amp; humaine, he ſpoyled hym of hys apparel, and (in contempt) naked, nailed him on a croſſe. Who long hangyng there in great payne &amp; penurye, dyd commit the reuenge of his innocencie, to God: &amp; with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable teares be wayled the miſerable eſtate of the City.<note place="margin">The Wane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Dane ouercommed with furious wrath, and wrapped in odible miſchiefe: dyd cauſe the natural &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret members of the deade, to be cut of, &amp; caſt at the face of him that was on the croſſe. Afterwarde they ſtroke him through the ſyde,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> where they tooke out his hart, &amp; ſlonge it in hys face. So great, ſo large, and ſo immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb facs="tcp:13623:21"/>was his irefull mynde, that he doubled hys tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, wyth violent force.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The family of Ribigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cruelly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted.</note>They chiefely perſecuted the whole houſe and family of Ribingus, towardes whom they vſed ſuch &amp; ſo much cruelty, that when there was no more lefte of ſufficient age for ſlaughter: they tooke the yonge children,<note place="margin">A pityfull murder of Chyldren.</note> &amp; tying their tender heare in knots, hanged them on cages. Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunding his flagitious Tormentours to cut of theyr heades, and let the deade carkaſes to fall on the fylthye ground. This done, be willed that al their bodies, wyth the reſt of thoſe that wer murthered, ſhould be brought into the Market place, where on with gaſing &amp; gapyng like a fury of hel, he fed his wrathful eyes, ſatiſfied hys monſtrous luſt,<note place="margin">A moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyble ſyght to loke vy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> &amp; fulfylled the deſyre of his moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mynde, with this his outtagious &amp; fierce miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Three dayes dyd their dead bodies lye there in moſte loth ſome wiſe, wrapped &amp; defiled all ouer in their owne clottred and congeled bloud.<note place="margin">Three daies dyd theyr dead bodies lie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mas ket place.</note> Thoſe that yet plunged in the panges of painful death, aſpiring with panting and feable breath to their fatal end: did with trembling fleſh (neither quicke nor dead) dequeth their wofull ſpirites to God. What eye ſo merciles could ſtay from teares, to behold ſuch torne bodies diſmembred of their lymmes, and to ſee ſuch pale &amp; wan viſages (as dead carkaſes do repreſent) whoſe innocent ghoſts (no doubt) the hoauens poſſeſt. No hart but Chriſtierns woulde haue executed ſuch dete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>table tirannies.<note place="margin">Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> hatte wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> No men but Monſters could haue bene apt inſtrumentes for ſuch a murther. As he was, ſuch was his ſeruauntes: For what he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they fulfylled in moſt extreme wyſe.</p>
               <p>After al this, Chriſtiern (not yet fully ſatiſfied, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly glutted in theſe facinorous factes) gaue ſtrayght
<pb facs="tcp:13623:22"/>commaundement, that their carkaſes ſhould be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtincking ſinckes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>k beab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>yed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yules.</note> filthy pits &amp; priuies, without the Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty. He drew the bodye of Steno out of his ſepulture, ſo much did the rage of tiranny gouerne him:<note place="margin">Stebi is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>en out of his graue</note> that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of deuouring, was like a gredy Hound. Who coulde be ſafe from his fury? or how was it poſſible for anye to be free from his malicious dedes: when as the cloſe and ſecret graues could not hide nor kepe their dead fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.</p>
               <p>When he had on this maner depopulated and waſted the City of men (leauing not one that the biting edge of weapon myght harme, nor ſparing of any that the twy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cord might ſtrangle) he turned all to rapine &amp; theft.<note place="margin">The cruel countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of homici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Wiues were ſpoyled of their Huſbandes, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes &amp; tender Sucklinges of their Parentes, the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of thoſe thinges they beſt loued, namelye theyr Children, their Friendes, their Kinred, and of all their goodes. Virgins were deſtoured, Maydens were raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, their auncient Monuments wer raſed, their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ruined, no prophane nor ſacred thyng was ſpared. Whyleſt the Tiraunt was executing of theſe deteſtable miſchiefes with in, he kept faſt the gates of the Citye, leaſt the horrible fame, &amp; cruel cry of their euyls, ſhoulde haue fled into the eares of the Countrye, whereby iuſt warres myght partly haue reuenged theyr moſte abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable doinges. What ſtuddes of teares ſhewrd down from euery mans eyes,<note place="margin">The lamen Racid of the Country.</note> with dolerous ſobs? What plun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging ſighes boiled out of euery mans breſt, with maſed myndes? What thundring noyſe roared foorth of euerye mans hart? What deſperat muſis, what terror, &amp; wyth what inward feare euery one was laden &amp; clogged with al, through the whole Country (when the horror of thys incredible newes was perfectlye reported vnto them?)
<pb facs="tcp:13623:22"/>there is none, but may iudge. Some Fathers lamented the loſſe of their Sonnes. Some Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bewayled the cruel end of their Fathers. Some Myues playned the woful death of their Huſbandes, &amp; ſome friendes ſoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed for the terrible tormentes of their Familiars, but generallye euerye one pitied the miſerable ſlaughter of their country men, and with great deſpight enuyed the hellyſh doynges of the Danes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtiern departeth from Stock holme.</note>When Chriſtiern had thus finiſhed the end of all hys murdriſh factes: he departed the City, and in his iorney went to an Abbey, called the New valley. Where of the Abbot and Monkes, he was honorably receiued, friend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly entertained, and gently vſed: hauing al thinges mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to him &amp; his at their deſire.<note place="margin">Chriſtiern commeth to an Abbey, called the New valley where he ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecuteth a crucl tirany</note> The Tiraunt did faine a great loue towardes them, taking verye thankfullye, their diligent curteſy. And beyng there on Candelmas day, he went to their Church, and heard ſeruice: neuer offering nor ſhewyng anye ſigne of miſchiefe, tyll ſuche time as their ceremonies wer done. The vnquenchable flaine of his ripe euyls &amp; peſtilent doinges, woulde not be by any meanes repreſſed nor extincted:<note place="margin">Tirani wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rooted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hart of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiern.</note> for the bloudy ſeede of murther was ſo rooted in his tyranous harte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hurle winde of miſchief, &amp; renting breath of vices, had ſhip wrackt in hym al princely vertues. For after he had receiued ſuch honorable chere, wyth an adiniracion of the Abbots prouiſion:<note place="margin">A cruell ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</note> Immediately when theyr ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſeruice was ended, he belched out his poyſoned na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, callyng the Monkes to account for his good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, rewarded them wyth bynding, beatyng, and drowning. The Abbot by fortune eſcaped their handes, and prouyng to ſaue his lyſe by ſwymmyng, the cruell and moſt parnicious companye of the Saylers, dyd ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13623:23"/>wounde hym, that looſyng hys ſtrengthe, he was lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe drowned.</p>
               <p>Thus thys Chriſtiern full gorged wyth the bloude of the Swecians,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> wyth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>dy ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>urns in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ark</note> and laden wyth rytches, ſlaughter, and ſpoyle, leauing a garyſon of Danes in the Caſtel of Stockholme: ſaylde wyth his horrible praye into Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke. He ſcourged Swecia with the plages of battell, theft, murder, &amp; al other kinde of miſcheuous euyls.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh ſury of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſtaue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounterfayt Byſhop.</note>Goſtaue the falſe and counterfaite Biſhop, deſyryng (contrary to his ſacred profeſſion) to excel in the bloudy fury of a ſoldiour, and delyghtynge in the daungerous broyles of battel, dyd thruſt out irradical, and violently pull vp by the rootes al ſuch as againſt his mynde poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt any ſpiritual poſſeſſions, or enioyed anye eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dignities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ How Prince Goſtaue eſcaped out of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, and after deliuered his Country.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſte noble Prince Goſtaue Erichſon, ſonne to Eric, nere of bloud to Charles Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutus, the laſt kyng of Swecia, &amp; Nephew to Steno Sture the Elder:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaue pryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke.</note> beyng yet a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtage (or rather a priſoner) in Denmarke, &amp; hearing of ſo many euyls &amp; calamities of his Countrye, going a hunting with other noble men of the Danes, he began to excogitate in his princely mynde, howe and by what meanes he might beſt eſcape &amp; ſteale away. Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offered,<note place="margin">He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell wyth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ourer.</note> &amp; ſequeſtring him ſelfe from the felowſhyp of the Hunters: he declined his natural nobilitye, to the courſe countenaunce of a country man, &amp; aparaled with the robes of a common laborour, he ioyned him ſelf to a
<pb facs="tcp:13623:23"/>Marchaunt, and fayned to be a Muleter or a keeper of Cattel, tyl ſuche tyme as he was eſcaped out of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Lubee, and from thence was tranſported into Swe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia. Where he did openly boldly and frankly declare, that he would reuenge the iniuries &amp; loſſes of his country, &amp; reſtore them againe to their auncient libertye, an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prite more then his youthfull yeres coulde compas, but that the ſtoutnes of his minde did anſwer to hys bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Moreouer, he was decked with ſuch temperaunce,<note place="margin">The vertues of Goſtaue.</note> honeſty, and manly prudence, as was rare to be founde in any of ſo grene and tender age. Therefore the fourth yere after the beginning of the bloudye warres of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiern, Prince Goſtaue chaunged his apparell, &amp; hauyng on the ruſty garmentes of a ragged country man: went about Swecia, declaring vnto them in how many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, curſed, and wicked euyls they were wrapped in, playnlye paynting foorthe the wretched eſtate of them al, leauing nor omitting any thing that might kyndle or encourage the Country &amp; Citizens to battel.<note place="margin">The perſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions of Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaue.</note> He dyd not forgette to tell them, that they were not borne for them ſelues, but for their Countrye, to whoſe ayde &amp; ſuccour they wer bound of duty to forſake no peryl, no daunger, nor any trauel, beyng then at poynt to periſhe wythout preſent helpe. He remembred them of all the facinorous factes that Chriſtiern had committed, &amp; alſo of the moſt great and greuous wickednes that hys flagitious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had executed, both againſt God &amp; man without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny renenge, which he to accompliſh with them, woulde haſard his lyfe, no whyt regardyng it, in reſpecte of the earneſt zeale he had to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vtility of his countrye men.<note place="margin">The come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e grace of Prince Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaue.</note> Moreouer the comelynes of his parſon dyd repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuche a Maieſty: that it declared his magnanimity
<pb facs="tcp:13623:24"/>to be adorned with a ſinguler valiant &amp; ſtout courage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Dale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karlions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yks people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Wherefore he tooke vpon him by their election, bothe to reuenge their wronges, &amp; alſo to ſet them at libertye. For the accompliſhment wherof, he leuyed ſoldiours of Dalckarly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt warlyke people of al Swecia. They dwel about the mountaines that deuideth Swecia fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Norway, where there be mynes of Syluer &amp; of Braſſe. Which mettal places doth quickly moue them,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Syluer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raſſe</note> &amp; chiefely ſtyrre them aboue al things to be fierce in reſiſting their enemyes. Goſtaue vſing the ſeruice of theſe men, went againſt the Danes, that laye in Gariſon in the Citye of Aoroſie,<note place="margin">The Danes lye in gary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> city of Aoroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y. The ſudayn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaue the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>op.</note> where they dyd muche harme wyth violating, vexing, and troubling of the whole country. Now Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaue (the Byſhop onely in name) &amp; Traitour to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, driuen into a great feare with thys ſoudeine &amp; new dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, ſought al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes he could how he might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw this begun enterpriſe of reuenge. But the noble, valiant,<note place="margin">The gentle nature of Prince Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaue.</note> and princely younge Goſtaue Erichſon, percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his entent, dyd ſend a Meſſenger to the Byſhoppe, friendlye exhorting hym to leaue of &amp; returne from hys old errors and treaſons. Conſidering that his countrye men (not long tyme paſt) had taſted the fruites of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, deteſtable, &amp; abhominable miſchiefes. The Biſhop receiued this gentle admonicion with ſuch arogancye,<note place="margin">The arogan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dain full pride of the byſhop.</note> &amp; pride: that reading his honorable &amp; curteous letters did ſpitefully caſt them down, and vnreuerently trode them vnder his feete. The magnificent Goſtaue (hauyng in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof) beyng of the bloud royal,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud royal</note> &amp; Nephewe to them who had woren the crownes of Swecia: nowe demaunding his rightful inheritaunce of thoſe that ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led it: was the more greued with the deſpite of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, which cauſed him to do that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of his regal
<pb facs="tcp:13623:24"/>auetority: that other wyſe he woulde haue redreſſed by hys clemency. He led a band of truſty &amp; choſen ſoldiours of the Dalekarlions agaynſt him &amp; his companye, who with ſmal power dyd ouercome him.<note place="margin">The Biſhop our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>throwe doth flye to Stockeholm</note> The Biſhop being thus ſubdued, with ſpedy flight went to Stockeholm, wher the reſt of the Danes lay in Gariſon. But they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the might of the Swecians daylye to encreaſe: dyd determine with this Traitour,<note place="margin">Goſtaue the Biſhop ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into Denmarke. The vnſtid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſcurteſt of Chriſtiern</note> to ſende for a newe army into the Country. With whiche promiſe he ſayled to his tirannical companion into Denmarke. Where he was (as wel worthy) neither friendly receiued, nor gent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly entertayned, nor after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was euer of any auctority or eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtiern. By what reaſon could he leaue, forſake, or ſhake of, the felowſhip &amp; ſociety of hym, who had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated their tyrannies, and ioyned their myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theuous myndes ſo often in one, being confederates to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in al their dampnable deedes. The king of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke was nothing inſeriour to him in al falſehed &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth, not onely to his enemies abroade, but alſo to hys ſubiectes at home. A buſy troubler of his country, wher in he was accordingly regarded: for wythin a whyle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys returne, he was depoſed from his kyngdome.<note place="margin">The Biſhop wandreth lyke an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, a iuſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>marke of traſen.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The crowne thus taken from the kyng, and he beyng thruſt out of the regal ſeat, Goſtaue the Biſhop without any glory or reuerence, lyke an abiect wandred through the country,<note place="margin">Chriſtiern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> lycke d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; ſo continued in Denmarke tyll hys dying day. Chriſtiern alſo poore &amp; nedy, for certaine yeares had no place to abyde in, but deſtitute of al kingly furniture, was compelied to place hys feete vnder other mene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; glad to banquet wyth other mens dainties, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſity and want driuing hym there vnto.</p>
               <p>Leauyng Chriſtiern thus a Stragle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt
<pb facs="tcp:13623:25"/>Goſtaue dyd leuy a mete and conuenient army of the Dalekariens,<note place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>h an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the Swecians, and the Gothes, &amp; fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the reſt of the Danes that were fled into Scon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia. He alſo beſieged Stockholme, wherein there was no men left,<note place="margin">Prince Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ue beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>h Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but onely the Gariſon of Chriſtiern. The wynnyng of thys City was very daungerons to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by aſſault: the place, the ſituacion, &amp; artificiall ſtrength of the towne reſiſtyng them. Notwithſtanding the vertue, myght and polecy of the Captayn was ſuch, that they forceably wan it, &amp; by aſſault dyd enter into it. The City thus taken, the valiaunt Prince Goſtaue dyd prudently conſider that al thinges was at a good point, the warres in euery place ended, &amp; the whole Realme (voyde of theyr enemyes) to be at quiet: therefore he did very honorably &amp; worthely reward his ſoldiours,<note place="margin">The wars ended, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaue magni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficentlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth his Soldiours.</note> euery one with ample &amp; large gyftes according to his good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. This done, he opened the ſeas agayne &amp; made ſafe and ſure nauigacion for all Saylers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The moſt noble / mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificent, and vertuous Prince Goſtaue, the onely deliuerer of his Country from al cruel bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, vyle ſeruitude and miſery: is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely elected Kyng.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the great goodnes that the moſt valiant,<note place="margin">By Prince Goſtaues vertue, he li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ected hys Country.</note> victorious, &amp; triumphaunt Goſtaue Erichſon dyd, by incredible trauayle (wyth great trouble of mynde, and paynfull labour of body) bryng to hys country: and becauſe he valiantly had reuenged the cruel wronges and horrible iniuries,
<pb facs="tcp:13623:25"/>where in his Country men were moſt miſerably wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: The Rulers of the kyngdome, that yet remayned, whoſe happy lyues had not taſted the terrible torments &amp; vehement furies of Chriſtiern:<note place="margin">Goſtaue is crowned Kynge of Swedland, Gothlande, &amp; Fynland. He is kyng by ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> election. By right he is horne to the crowne.</note> and al the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Swecia &amp; Gothland, with one voyce &amp; one con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent, both by right &amp; deſerte, dyd crowne hym kyng. And generally wyth glad mindes &amp; ioyfull hartes they gaue him the Imperial ſword: as one whoſe noble actes had worthely merited (both by ſucceſſion &amp; election) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal place of his predeceſſors. By ryght he was lawfull kyng: no leſſe nobly borne in birth, then valiaunt &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent in dede. Of no baſer bloud, then his haught at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes witneſſed. Of no meaner parentage, then hys honorable doinges declared, &amp; of no lower race, then his princely vertues ſhewed.<note place="margin">By deſert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be bought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the crowne.</note> By deſert he dearelye bought the kyngdome: For he deliuered them from the moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter bondage, &amp; vyle thraldome of theyr cruel enemyes, he aſſured their lyues from thoſe that wold haue murdred them. He reſtored their auncient fame, from thoſe that had diſfamed them. He liberted their Cities,<note place="margin">The pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res he did to his country</note> from thoſe that had diſfrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched them. He garded their goods from thoſe that would haue ſpoyled them, and finallye he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them from domeſtical peril and alſo defended them from outward daunger.</p>
               <p>This prudent Prince by his wyſdome, power &amp; pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, with an inuincible mynde, for the reuenge &amp; reſtoring of his Country,<note place="margin">Nature made hym, his vertues cald hym<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; fortune pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed hym in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gall eſtate.</note> paſſed through a thouſand perils (ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymes on the rough &amp; ragged rockes of the Danes tiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, &amp; ſometimes almoſt ſwaloed vp with the deuouring ſandes of enuy) before he could attayne to the royall typ of his apointed eſtate. For the which Nature at the firſt had made him, vertue had cald him, &amp; fortune had in the
<pb facs="tcp:13623:26"/>end brought him. Now al thoſe that wylled wel to their Country, preferring honorable concord, before ciuill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencion, regarding publicke vtilitye more then common ſpoile,<note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> loſts &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>throwers of Common wealthes.</note> and, vnleſſe it were ſuche that were enemyes to reſt &amp; quietnes, foes to the good, &amp; friendes to the euyll, greedy catchers of other mens lyuinges, &amp; prodigal wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their own, ſowers of ſedicion, &amp; reapers of diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, ſtyrrers and mouers to al ſtryfe &amp; miſchiefe (as no common welth is cleare without ſome of them) excepte theſe hop loſtes, not one but greatly dyd reioyce, &amp; made their humble prayers to God:<note place="margin">They pray for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of hys raygne.</note> That his Maieſty might long raygne among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home with euerlaſting peace and tranquiſlity, &amp; abroade againſt hys &amp; their enemies with great conqueſt &amp; victorye: &amp; chiefly that his prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perſon myght be ſure in both. Wyſhing hys lyfe ſo to ſhyne in prudent vertue, that he myght be a myrrour &amp; lyuely example to al mighty Kynges &amp; rulers, whereby he ſhould for euer be worthely ſaluted (&amp; wyth the ſwift thundring tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe of fame reported) for the beſt &amp; happieſt</p>
               <p>After this triumphant maner, the noble king Goſtaue receiued the crowne of Swetheland, Gothland, &amp; Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.<note place="margin">With what p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ce Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d his country</note> Which Regimentes he did gouerne by ſuch politik wiſdome, and princelye prouidence, that ioyning wyth hys regal auctority great and laudable vertues, he euer mayntayned and noriſhed aboue al thynges, peace, loue and concord.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Not withſtanding the Sucalandes a few yeres paſt dyd a lytle trouble &amp; vexe the country. Which ſedicion was by his prudent wyſedome ſo prouided for, and by hys diligent induſtry ſo pecified, that they flory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed wyth happy peace &amp; deſired tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquiſity.<note place="margin">The ioyneth godly, wyſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to hym</note> To the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmyng and luculently eſtably Kyng whereof, was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen certayne men, both godly, wyſe and worthye, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:13623:26"/>graue counſels the Kyng dyd cal to his kyngdome wyth great loue and fauour: Namely George Norman,<note place="margin">George nor ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Oliuer Holmens.</note> and Oliuer Holme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, both ſingulerly wel learned. The firſt for hys noble giftes of the mynde, wherein he dyd excel, and alſo for his godly knowledge in the ſcriptures: he was made Tutor and Scolemaiſter to the moſt prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and valiant Eric now Kyng of Swecia,<note place="margin">George Nor man Tutor to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ric, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owe king of ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dia, and to Duke Iohn his brethee.</note> &amp; to Duke Iohn hys Brother. And moreouer, for hys great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and excellency of wyt was elected one of King Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaues priuy counſel. The other named Oliuer Holme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, beſyde lys ſincere and perfecte vnderſtandyng of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures, and alſo his knowledge of other notable hiſtories, was an expert and rethoricall Preacher.</p>
               <p>Theſe two wyth others their lyke, dyd the King choſe to be the principall members of hys kyngdome.<note place="margin">Goſtaue did proſper w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gloryo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s fame.</note> Whoſe raigne could not by any meanes decay, but proſper with glorious fame, hauyng ſuche graue Counſellers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct hys doynges, and preparyng ſuche inſtrumentes for the maintenaunce of hys regal eſtate. What expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion was to be looked for in thoſe tender and youthfull yeares of the moſt noble Eric (that yet were vnperfect) not onely hys princely and vertuous redynes (which as then by report began to bud out) but alſo the good educa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and learned enſtruction of his Tutor,<note place="margin">Occaſion why there was good &amp; greet hope of the noble Prince E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> he beyng en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and brought vp in lyke condicion and lyke inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion wyth hym, myght brynge thys doubt in queſtion: Whether the Kyng or hys Country had moſt cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce. The Father for that he had gotten ſuch a Child to rule after hym: or the Country for that they ſhould haue ſuch a Prince, both learned &amp; wyſe to raygne ouer them, he declared beyng young, what fruites he would yeld in age. Notwythſtanding, becauſe Princes do often dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate
<pb facs="tcp:13623:27"/>from perfect Nobilitye, and altering their noble nature from the beginning, do incurre into a thouſande euyls in the end (though his vertuous doinges hitherto haue yet ſet forth no ſuch lykelyhoode) I leaue hys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent praiſes to the good or euil deſertes of his actes here after. Not douting or it be long, to ſee the valiaunt and proſperous raygne of his Father in publicke print, who ruled the Swedians, the Gothes and the Vandoles the ſpace of <hi>.38.</hi> yeares. Yelding nature her due, the yeare of Chriſt <hi>.1560.</hi> and left the crowne to his Sonne Eric, the <hi>14.</hi> kyng of that name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ The deſcripcion of Finland, after the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Seba. Mounſter.</head>
               <p>FInlande is called a fayre Countrye, becauſe it is more pleſaunter then Swecia. Plini ſeemeth to name it Finnonia, of the bowing arme or boſome of the ſea Finnonicus. It is ſo large a Countrye, that it once was called a kyngdome, but now it hath onely the title of a Dukedome. The Sclauous in this paſſed age did inhabite there, whych nacion vſed the Grecian lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſo long as Moſchus was Lorde ouer them. But now it is vnder the crown of Swecia, and doth vſe the rites and ceremonies of the Weſtern Churche. Muche wyne is tranſported thither, out of Spayne, by the ſea Balthic, which the people of the Country much deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, onely to exhillerat their myndes. The inhabitants profeſſed Chriſte after the Swecians, vnder Eric then king of Swecia. This Country doth excell Swedia, in corne and grain, both for plenty and goodnes, becauſe it is for the moſt part playne, and not ſo fenny nor hylly as
<pb facs="tcp:13623:27"/>Swecia is. There be trym townes in Finland, as Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta, a towne fortified for the warres, Abo their Byſhops ſea, Raſbing, Viburg, Karelia a Dukedome. Abo is not far diſtant from Vplandia, Viburg is ſituated at the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treme borders and fartheſt boundes of all Fynlande, towards and againſt the Ruſſes and Muſchouites. It is the chiefe and principal place where theyr Soldiours and Gariſous do lye, that defendes and kepes thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple from inuadyng the Countrye. It is alſo a Marte towne of great trafficke, whereunto the Ruthines doo often frequent. They ſaye that the Northe pole dothe ryſe ouer this town, aboue the horiſont <hi>.61.</hi> degrees and a halfe, and they nomber the length to be <hi>.78.</hi> They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the degrees of Stockeholme to be in breadth <hi>.61.</hi> and in length <hi>.64.</hi> The Finnons haue continual warres wyth the Muſcouites in the arme or boſome of the ſea Finnonicus: vſyng in Summer the ayde of Shyppes, and in Mynter they combat vpon the Iſe. Howe popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous was this Country and others lying aboute it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye great and wyſe men doo wytnes, as Methodius, Martir, Iordanus, Gothus, and Paulus Diaconus, the which Aucthors do wryte that this people dyd ſwarme out lyke Bees. And they call theſe Northe Regions the Store houſe or Garnar of Nacions, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of them are proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe names folowing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13623:28"/>
               <list>
                  <item>The Gothes.</item>
                  <item>The Oſtrogothes</item>
                  <item>The Veſtrogoths</item>
                  <item>The Gepides.</item>
                  <item>The Samogets.</item>
                  <item>The Maſſagets.</item>
                  <item>The Hunes.</item>
                  <item>The Amaſons.</item>
                  <item>The Cimbrians.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>The Parthians.</item>
                  <item>The Swedians.</item>
                  <item>The Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gobardia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</item>
                  <item>The Turcilingia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</item>
                  <item>The Auarians.</item>
                  <item>The Herulians.</item>
                  <item>The Winulians.</item>
                  <item>The Sueuians.</item>
                  <item>The Bulgarians.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>The Suicers.</item>
                  <item>The Taliphalia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</item>
                  <item>The Danes.</item>
                  <item>The Sclauons.</item>
                  <item>The Rugians.</item>
                  <item>The Alanians.</item>
                  <item>The Burgundia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</item>
                  <item>The Sembrians.</item>
                  <item>The Liuonians.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>The Scirians.</item>
                  <item>The Nortmania<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</item>
                  <item>The Pictians.</item>
                  <item>The Carpians.</item>
                  <item>The Caibians.</item>
                  <item>The Cimerians.</item>
                  <item>The Daciaus:</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Inhabitantes of Fynland do ſpeake twoo ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry languages. From Viburg to Berga or Sibb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na, they do for the moſt part ſpeake the Sclauon tong, but nere the Sea coaſtes they vſe at thys preſent the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian language, and in the myddeſt of the Country, theyr proper ſpeeche. And on the lymeth and borders, they oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy both. Wherefore in manye places their Preachers doo preache and interpretate the Scriptures in bothe tounges. The Swedian language, and the ſame that the Gothes, the Danes, &amp; the Norwaies do vſe, is one, but that they haue ſundry pronouncinges, and propes
<pb facs="tcp:13623:28"/>accentes in voyce. They do alſo agree muche wyth the Germaines, as for example ſuche as can ſpeake or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Germain tong, may here reade the Lordes prayer in the Swecian language, whereby they maye iudge the difference of their ſpeeches.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="swe" type="Pater_Noster">
               <head>¶ The Lordes prayerin the Swecian Language.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ader vuar ſom er i himulum, heiligat vuar de dit namen, tilkomen tit rike, ſckedin vuillige ſom i himulum ſo opo iordene, vuar taglig brodh gif os itag verlath os vuaren ſchuld ſom vni verlatten vuare ſckuldiger, och in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledhos icke i freſtilſe, vt an lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ i froonda. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Iohn Awdely, dwelling in litle Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Streete, by great S. Bartelmewes. Anno <hi>.1561.</hi> The <hi>.28.</hi> of October.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
